crisistextline.org 2016-06-10

# Crisis Text Line | Crisis Text Line

Last Updated: May 16, 2016 at 3:30 pm EST

**IF YOU ARE IN DANGER OR NEED EMERGENCY HELP, CALL 911 OR YOUR LOCAL AUTHORITIES.**

## Scope; Acceptance of Terms and Conditions (“Terms”)

Before using CTL, please read the following. By accessing or using CTL you agree to the Terms of Service (“Terms”) and Privacy Policy (“Privacy Policy”) described below. These Terms govern your access and use of CTL. You may contact CTL by e-mail at info@crisistextline.org with questions about these Terms. If you don’t agree to the Terms, you may not use CTL. You can find a list of other hotlines at [CrisisTextLine.org/hotlines](http://crisistextline.org/hotlines).

## Modification of the Terms and Privacy Policy

This statement may be modified from time to time. Why? Because we care about you and we want to be super thoughtful about the Terms and how CTL works. Any changes will be effective immediately upon our posting them here at CrisisTextLine.org. (So, yeah, if you are reading these words, that means we posted them. So, there you go.) Your use of CTL constitutes your acceptance of these Terms and Privacy Policy.

Each time that you first send a text message to CTL, you’ll receive a couple automated reply text message(s) with a link to our current Terms and Privacy Policy so you may review them before continuing to use CTL. Using CTL after receiving those text message(s) shall constitute your acceptance of the Terms and Privacy Policy.

## Nature and Use of Information Provided through This Service

We’re here to try to help you out of crisis–that means, to go from a “hot” moment to a “cool headed calm,” and we try to help equip you with tools to move yourself from “hot” to “cool” if you face a crisis in the future.

But remember, your participation in CTL does not constitute an attorney-client relationship, a doctor-patient relationship, a therapist-client relationship, a therapist-patient relationship or any other sort of confidential relationship. We’re not your doctor, your mom, or even your best friend. CTL is not a substitute for professional health care. If you believe you are experiencing a medical emergency, immediately speak with an adult, or call your doctor or 911. And, if you are experiencing a clinical or long-term issue, you should consult a medical professional.

CTL and any of our employees, Crisis Counselors, or agents are not responsible for any decisions, or results of the decisions that you make while, as a result of, or after participating in CTL. This includes whether you choose to seek or not seek professional care, or to modify or terminate specific treatment that you are currently receiving based on the information provided by this service. You are the boss of your own happiness. We can ask questions and nudge you in a healthy direction, but only YOU control your own actions, reactions, and words. (You can tweet that last bit. It is strong.)

## Risks, Use of Service

You assume all risk for use of this service. CTL and any of our employees, Crisis Counselors, agents, service providers, or any other entities with whom CTL has contracted shall have no liability for (1) actions taken by you or a third party, or not taken by you or a third party, or (2) the unavailability of this service, and you agree to indemnify us and hold us harmless for damages arising out of (1) your use of CTL, (2) your breach of these Terms, (3) your violation of the law, (4) claims asserted by third parties, which, if proven, would place you in breach of these Terms or (5) information provided by you through CTL. Without limiting the foregoing, in no event shall CTL be liable for any special, incidental, consequential, exemplary or indirect damages.

This service is provided on an “as is” basis and “as available” basis. (But we try to be awesome and we are constantly improving.) CTL and its service providers expressly disclaim all warranties of any kind, whether express or implied, including, without limitation, the implied warranties of merchantability, fitness for a particular purpose and non-infringement, and, without limiting the generality of the foregoing, makes no warranty that CTL will a) meet your requirements; b) be uninterrupted, timely, secure, or error-free; or c) meet your expectations. The foregoing disclaimers of liability apply to all damages or injury, including those caused by any failure of performance, error, omission, interruption, deletion, defect or delay in operation or transmission, whether for breach of contract, tortious behavior, including negligence, or any other cause of action.

## Prohibited Uses; Right to Terminate Access

You may use CTL only for lawful purposes and in accordance with these Terms. You agree to use the CTL only for lawful and legitimate purposes. You agree not to use CTL:

  * In any way that violates any applicable federal, state, local and international law or regulation;
  * For the purpose of exploiting, harming or attempting to exploit or harm minors in any way by exposing them to inappropriate content, asking for personal information or otherwise;
  * To threaten, harass, or otherwise inappropriately abuse CTL, its employees, partners, agents, subcontractors, Crisis Counselors, or others;
  * To send, knowingly receive, upload, download, use or re-use any content which does not comply with these Terms;
  * To “spam,” gather or attempt to gather personal information belonging to users or others for the purposes of spamming, marketing, selling to third parties, or otherwise abusing CTL or its users;
  * To impersonate or attempt to impersonate another person or entity; or
  * To engage in any other conduct that restricts or inhibits anyone’s use or enjoyment of the Services, or which, as determined by us, may harm Synergy or users of the Services or expose them to liability; or
  * To otherwise attempt to interfere with the proper working of CTL.

CTL reserves the right to terminate your access to CTL if you violate these Terms, including by engaging in the prohibited uses described above. (Simply put, please don’t be a jerk. We are doing our very best to help CTL users move from hot to cool. If you are mean to our people or you abuse our service, we are going to stop you from using it.)

CTL may also terminate your access to our service. For example, we might determine that you’d be better served by a different kind of support or that you require service beyond those that we can reasonably provide to you.

CTL further reserves the right to terminate CTL or your access to it, for any other reason, at our sole discretion. (But we’ll try to be cool about it.)

## Governing Law

These Terms and the provision of CTL is governed solely by, and shall be interpreted according to, the laws of the State of New York without giving effect to principles of conflict of law. Both parties consent to the exclusive jurisdiction of the state and federal courts located in the city of New York, borough of Manhattan. (Basically, we <3 New York.)

## Severability; Entire Agreement

If a Court finds any provision of these Terms to be invalid or unenforceable, that provision shall be enforced to the maximum extent possible and the remaining Terms shall remain in full force and effect. These Terms constitute the entire agreement between you and CTL, superseding any other written or oral agreements or understandings. (Basically, this is a fancy way of saying the stuff you’re reading now is what you and CTL agree about, and even if we later fight about some of words, the rest of the words still stick around.)

## Privacy and Security

We take your privacy and security very seriously, so we employ reasonable security controls (including encryption) to help protect your information. Despite these protections, SMS remains an imperfectly secure environment and there are some reallllly persistent hackers out there. We are trying super hard, but CTL cannot guarantee complete protection from intruders or interceptors (fancy words for hackers and other bad people). So, you agree to use CTL and submit information at your own risk, and you agree that CTL has no liability regarding anyone’s unauthorized access to CTL or the data associated with it.

Additionally, we care about the privacy and safety of our staff and Crisis Counselors. In using this service, you agree to not communicate with our Crisis Counselors outside of the service that CTL provides. If you have questions, comments or feedback for us, please email info@crisistextline.org.

Last Updated: February 9, 2016 at 4:10 pm EST

## INTRODUCTION; SCOPE

At Crisis Text Line (“CTL,” “We,” “Us”), our goal is to help people in crisis. We’re here to try to help you out of crisis–that means, to go from a “hot” moment to a “cool headed calm,” and we try to help equip you with tools to move yourself from “hot” to “cool” if you face a crisis in the future.

Importantly, we also want you to feel safe when you text with us. We want you to share all those awful things that are making you feel awful, so we can help you feel better!

Your privacy and security are very important to us. To make sure we’re doing everything we can to secure your information, we communicate our privacy and security guidelines to CTL employees and Crisis Counselors, and employees and Crisis Counselors at our third party service providers. We stringently enforce these privacy safeguards.

This Privacy Policy governs your use of CTL, describes what information we collect on CTL, and explains how we use, transfer and store your information after we collect it. This policy will inform you if and to whom we disclose any of that information, and what choices you have in how we use that information. So before using CTL, please read the following.

## YOUR CONSENT AND CHANGES IN PRIVACY POLICY

By using CTL, you agree to the practices outlined in this Privacy Policy. CTL may change this Privacy Policy from time to time, so please consult it regularly for any such changes. Any changes will be effective immediately upon our posting them to our website at CrisisTextLine.org. Your use of CTL after any such changes have been posted shall constitute your acceptance of the revised Privacy Policy and Terms.

Each time that you first send a text message to CTL, you’ll receive a couple automated reply text message(s) with a link to our current Terms and Privacy Policy so you may review them before continuing to use CTL, using CTL after receiving those text message(s) shall constitute your acceptance of the Terms and Privacy Policy.

## COLLECTION AND USE OF PERSONALLY IDENTIFIABLE INFORMATION

“Personally Identifiable Information” is data that can be used to uniquely identify you, such as your full name or home address. During your use of CTL you may be prompted (but never required) to voluntarily provide Personally Identifiable Information, including but not limited to, your home address or email address. We will ONLY ask for this if we believe it would help us to better serve you.

While we may collect Personally Identifiable Information, we will not sell or license to any third party any Personally Identifiable Information we receive from you, and will not share it with any third parties except as noted below.

CTL uses the information it collects about you to, among other things, improve CTL, contact you, provide anonymous reporting internally, and fulfill your requests, including but not limited to referrals to other services. In other words, we collect information so we can provide you and others like you with a better service, helping move more people in crisis from “hot” to “cool.”  
The following section provides examples of the types of Personally Identifiable Information CTL may collect and how we may use it.

## WHAT PERSONALLY IDENTIFIABLE INFORMATION WE COLLECT

We do not collect any Personally Identifiable Information from you other than the phone number you text us from and that which you voluntarily provide to us. Some of the types of Personally Identifiable Information that we may request include:

  * When you contact CTL, we may request information including your name, age, and zip code.
  * When you contact CTL about a friend, family member, or other person in need of our services, we may request the information you provide about those people such as name and zip code.
  * In situations where you or someone else is in danger or in need of emergency help, we may request your current location, or the current location of the person in danger.

## HOW WE USE YOUR PERSONALLY IDENTIFIABLE INFORMATION

We use Personally Identifiable Information to help us develop, deliver, and improve our products, services, content, and advertising.

  * If you choose to receive follow-up email messages or text messages from us, the Personally Identifiable Information we collect may be used to notify you of relevant information or volunteer opportunities. If you no longer wish to receive messages, you may opt out at any time by texting the word STOP.
  * We may also use Personally Identifiable Information for internal purposes such as auditing, data analysis, and research to improve CTL’s products, services, and communications.
  * We may also use your information to help us personalize your experience with us and to operate, maintain and improve the features and functionality of our service.

## COLLECTION AND USE OF NON-PERSONALLY IDENTIFIABLE INFORMATION

We also collect non-Personally Identifiable Information, which is data that cannot be directly used to identify or contact you. We may collect, use, transfer, and disclose non-Personally Identifiable Information for any purpose, including but not limited to improving volunteer services, disclosing to third parties to generate support for CTL, or as required by law.

Below are examples of non-Personally Identifiable Information that we collect and how we may use it:

  * We may collect information such as age, gender, language, zip code, area code, and the time zone where a phone is being used to contact CTL to better understand behavior and improve our service.
  * We also may collect information regarding usage of CTL such as the conversation volume, average length of conversation, and other data. This information is aggregated and helps us conduct internal research so we can improve the quality of our service.

## DISCLOSURE TO THIRD PARTIES

At times we may make certain Personally Identifiable Information available to strategic partners that work with us.

### Police and EMS

It’s our goal to support you in staying safe and healthy and to do so in the least invasive way possible (read: we don’t want to intrude in your life!). If a crisis counselor identifies imminent harm to yourself or someone else (you have the desire, plan, and means) or suspects abuse or neglect, they let you know they’re concerned about your safety. At this point, they might ask you where you are or what your name is. They’ll continue to work to support you, and if they feel like you might not be able to keep yourself safe, they may contact local police or EMS. We’re not here to tell on you, or rat you out, but we are here to do our best to support you in staying healthy and safe.

### CRISIS COUNSELORS

We operate CTL in conjunction with volunteer and staff crisis counselors (“Crisis Counselors”). Any information, including Personally Identifiable Information, that you share with CTL may be viewed by CTL staff or Crisis Counselors for quality control and to better assist you with your crisis.

If you provide feedback through an anonymous feedback survey, that feedback may also be shared with CTL Staff and Crisis Counselors. We want to provide an awesome service, so we are hungry to learn from your feedback!

### OUTSIDE REFERRALS

Sometimes, we may refer you to another hotline or program. There are some really great programs out there! We will give you their contact info…but we will NOT give them your contact info. So, its up to you if you want to use the referral. If you would like to receive support from other services, please note that different rules may apply to their use or disclosure of Personally Identifiable Information. We do not control the privacy policies of others. We encourage you to ask questions before you disclose your Personally Identifiable Information to others.

### OTHER THIRD PARTIES; LEGAL PROCESSES

In certain narrow circumstances, we may disclose Personally Identifiable Information we collect from you to additional third parties to the extent necessary to: (A) to comply with the law or in response to a subpoena, court order, government request, or other legal process; (B) to protect the interests, rights, safety, or property of CTL, its affiliates, employees, or agents, including but not limited to Crisis Counselors; (C) to enforce this Privacy Policy or Terms; (D) in connection with a merger, acquisition, liquidation, or corporate divestiture of CTL or its affiliates, or (E) to address fraud, security, technical issues, or to operate CTL or its infrastructure systems properly.

Note that CTL’s staff and Crisis Counselors are located across the United States, and may not be licensed in your state or trained in your state’s law. Other state laws may apply to your communications, and those state laws may not protect your communications to the same degree, or in the same way, as the laws of your state.

### RESEARCHERS

As of Feb 16, 2016, we have created a formal process for sharing information about conversations with researchers at universities and other institutions. We share data with trusted researchers only when it will result in insights that create a better experience for our texters. We follow a set of best practices for data sharing based on the University of Michigan’s Interuniversity Consortium of Social and Political Research, one of the largest open data projects in the U.S., which includes stringent ethical, legal, and security checks. For more details, see our policies for [open data collaborations](http://www.crisistextline.org/open-data).

## RETENTION OF INFORMATION

CTL retains data for reasons including but not limited to improving the quality of our crisis counseling, complying with federal research grant and other reporting requirements, and creating open data collaboration tools, such as [www.crisistrends.org](http://www.crisistrends.org/).

Retention policies and security measures match the sensitivity of the data. We categorize data into three types, based on chance of containing Personally Identifiable Information:

  * The first two, Conversation Level and Actor Level, do not contain Personally Identifiable Information. These will be retained indefinitely.
  * The third, Message Level, may contain Personally Identifiable Information, including message content and phone number.This will be retained for 7 years, then scrubbed.
  * Non-Identifiers: Data could not identify an individual, directly or indirectly
  * You may request more information by contacting us at info@CrisisTextLine.org.

## HOW WE PROTECT YOUR PERSONALLY IDENTIFIABLE INFORMATION

CTL cares about you and the security of your Personally Identifiable Information. We take reasonable precautions, including administrative, technical, and physical measures, to protect your Personally Identifiable Information from loss, theft, misuse, unauthorized access, disclosure, alteration, and destruction. We store all information on secure servers only accessible by approved CTL employees and third parties pursuant to the practices described above.

We employ different security techniques to protect your Personally Identifiable Information from unauthorized access, including standard encryption practices. However, perfect security does not exist anywhere, including for text messaging/SMS data. Although we believe we take appropriate measures to safeguard against unauthorized disclosures of information, we cannot assure you that your Personally Identifiable Information or communications with CTL will never be disclosed in a manner inconsistent with this policy, and make no representations or warranties regarding the sufficiency of our security measures to prevent unauthorized access or interception by third parties.

## YOU SHOULD ALSO PROTECT YOURSELF

Always be careful and responsible regarding your Personally Identifiable Information. We are not responsible for, and cannot control, what others not affiliated with CTL, CCs, or Crisis Counselors do with information you provide to them.

One suggestion: you might want to delete CTL conversations from your phone. You might even want to clear us from your history and make sure we are not saved in your contact list. We’re not mad. We totally understand if you want to take these steps and others, to ensure that your relationship to CTL remains your business.

## ACCESS/CHANGES TO PERSONALLY IDENTIFIABLE INFORMATION

You may request that we delete your Personally Identifiable Information, such as last name, physical address, zip code, phone number, and texts/message transcripts by texting in the keyword LOOFAH to 741-741, after which you will be prompted to confirm your request.

We will make reasonable efforts to process deletion requests promptly, but may decline to process requests that are unreasonably repetitive, require unreasonable technical effort, jeopardize the privacy of you or others, are otherwise impractical, or which would conflict with applicable laws or an ongoing law enforcement matter.

## GOVERNING LAW; INTERNATIONAL USERS

These Terms and the provision of CTL is governed solely by, and shall be interpreted according to, the laws of the State of New York without giving effect to principles of conflict of law. Both parties consent to the exclusive jurisdiction of the state and federal courts located in the city of New York, borough of Manhattan. (Basically, we <3 New York.)

CTL is operated in the United States. If you are located outside of the United States, please be aware that any information you provide will be collected in or transferred to the United States. By using CTL and/or providing us with your information, you consent to that collection and transfer.

## SEVERABILITY; ENTIRE AGREEMENT

If a Court finds any provision of these Terms to be invalid or unenforceable, that provision shall be enforced to the maximum extent possible and the remaining Terms shall remain in full force and effect. These Terms constitute the entire agreement between you and CTL, superseding any other written or oral agreements or understandings. (Basically, this is a fancy way of saying the stuff you’re reading now is what you and CTL agree about, and even if we later fight about some words, the rest of the words still stick around.)

## CONTACT US

If you have any questions or concerns about our Privacy Policy or the privacy practices described here, please contact: info@crisistextline.org.
